https://www.healthdatamanagement.com/news/lawmakers-va-apps-pose-privacy-risk-to-veterans-healthcare-data

VA apps pose privacy risk to veterans’ healthcare data | Health Data Management
Resources
© 2020 Arizent. All rights reserved.
Email
Copy Link URLCopied!
Print
Register now
The increasing use of apps provided by the Department of Veterans Affairs is meant to improve access to patient health and benefits information in convenient digital platforms. However, members of Congress are worried that this electronic data is vulnerable. “When a veteran downloads an app from the VA’s app store, how much personal information does the VA receive?” asked Rep. Susie Lee (D-Nev.), chair of the House Veterans’ Affairs Subcommittee on Technology Modernization, during a hearing on Wednesday. “What is the process used to determine what is minimally required?”Lee noted that her subcommittee studied some of the VA’s apps, many of which “require significant, elevated permissions and access to users’ data or devices.” As a result, she contends that these apps as currently configured “may be excessive and unnecessary invasions of a veteran’s privacy” and may put them at risk for identity theft.
“Why do these apps need access to location, a user’s photos, calendars, contacts and other information?” asked Lee. “Are these permissions necessary for its function?”Rep. Jim Banks (R-Ind.), ranking member of the subcommittee, observed that personally identifiable information and protected health information are increasingly stored in the cloud and provided to external apps. “Business Associate Agreements stipulate how patient data will be used but patients rarely have any idea what those agreements say,” said Banks. “And, notices of privacy practices are often vague.”In that regard, Lee pointed out that the privacy policy for one VA app is “988 words of legalese with clauses about incidental or consequential damages.”However, Paul Cunningham, the VA’s Chief Information Security Officer and Chief Privacy Officer, testified that veterans voluntarily share their personal information with the agency—including personally identifiable information and protected health information."When Veterans do provide information, VA will not disclose that information to outside parties except at the request of the veteran or as authorized by law,” according to Cunningham’s testimony. “Additionally, VA.gov will never sell or rent personal information to outside parties. Violation of any part of this policy within the department would result in corrective actions including possible dismissal and could result in a criminal charge against the offending employee or contractor.”While the VA must often share data with third party partners, Cunningham said the VA “stipulates the terms for acceptable use” in its policies and Business Associate Agreements and that “partners must meet these requirements and protect our data as closely as we do."
By
Greg Slabodkin
Facebook
Twitter
LinkedIn
Email
Print
Show more sharing options
Share
Close extra sharing options
Facebook
Twitter
LinkedIn
Email
Copy Link URLCopied!
Print
Reprint
For reprint and licensing requests for this article, click here.
Tags
Data privacyAppsThe VAPatient dataHIPAAPersonally identifiable informationProtected health information
Trending
HIT
What should lie ahead for healthcare IT in the next decade
As Health Data Management wraps up 27 years of reporting on the healthcare information technology industry today, it gives me a chance to pause and reflect, and to look hopefully toward the future for the industry.
By Fred Bazzoli
February 13
EHR implementations
House panel to hold hearing on VA delay of first EHR go-live
The chair of the House subcommittee charged with legislative oversight of the VA’s Cerner electronic health record implementation is concerned about the agency’s decision to delay the EHR’s initial go-live.
By Greg Slabodkin
February 13
Diseases and conditions
Health standards organizations help codify novel coronavirus info
As part of the global effort to manage and contain the coronavirus response, two global health standards organizations have introduced new content.
By Fred Bazzoli
February 13
MORE FROM HEALTH DATA MANAGEMENT
Value-based care
Apervita’s NCQA approval helps health plans speed VBC analysis
House bill would require national telehealth strategy from feds
By Greg Slabodkin
February 11
Interoperability
Sequoia Project to create work group to help develop Common Agreement
By Greg Slabodkin
February 11
